Finding Aid for Michel Oksenberg papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michel Oksenberg papers
1960-2001
Oksenberg, Michael, 1938-
861112 Aa 2
Michel Oksenberg was a Professor of Political Science at the University of Michigan, and a specialist in China and Sino-American relations. His papers contain correspondence concerning professional activities, committee assignments, conferences; publications, project files, book reviews, and periodical articles; also interview notes with refugees from the People's Republic of China conducted in Hong Kong.
68 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers of Professor Oksenberg (Donor No. 6466 ) have been received in various accessions, between 1980 and 2002.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Michel Charles Oksenberg was born October 12, 1938 in Antwerp, Belgium. He later emigrated to the United States where he was raised in Tallahassee, Florida, and where he became a naturalized citizen. Oksenberg graduated from Leon High School in Tallahassee in 1956, then went on to Swarthmore College, where he received a B.A. with honors in 1960, and then to Columbia University, where he received his M.A. in 1963 and his Ph.D. in 1969. As an undergraduate, he majored in political science, though he also studied philosophy and economics. At Columbia, he specialized in foreign political institutions (China, Japan, and the USSR) with a minor in American government. He learned Chinese and French at this time.
Oksenberg began his professional career at Stanford University as acting assistant professor of political science (1966-1968). He then returned to Columbia as assistant professor (1968-1971) and later was associate professor (1971-1974) in that college's East Asian Institute. In 1973, he took on added responsibilities as adjunct associate professor at the University of Michigan's Center for Chinese Studies, and in 1974, he was appointed associate professor at the University of Michigan.
Oksenberg's principle interest as a scholar has been in the government and institutions of the People's Republic of China (PRC). His dissertation at Columbia concerned local and rural government in China, and he has since authored numerous articles and book reviews in the field. He traveled to China in 1964-1965, and again in 1971-1972, and while there, he studied at the Universities Service Center in Kowloon (Hong Kong) and made contacts with a number of Chinese scholars. Oksenberg made numerous subsequent trips to China.
Since 1968, Oksenberg has served on both the executive committee and the board of directors of the National Committee on U.S. - China Relations. From 1970 to 1974, he was a member of the board of directors of the Association for Asian Studies, and since 1971, he has been on the Council of Foreign Relations. He has been a consultant to the Rand Corporation (1967-1973) and the Ford Foundation (1971), and was a member of the Preliminary Screening Committee of the Foreign Area Fellowship Program for Asia (1967-1971). He has served on the editorial boards of several scholarly journals, including China Quarterly (1970- ), Chinese Law and Government (1970- ), and the Journal of Asian Studies (1972- ). He belongs to the American Political Science Association and has participated in the Social Science Research Council (particularly its Joint Committee on Contemporary China). He has also been a managing member of the executive board of Swarthmore College.
In 1977, Oksenberg took a two-year leave of absence from the University of Michigan to become a member of the National Security Council, where he was actively involved with the normalization of relations between the U.S. and PRC governments. He returned to the University in February 1980 and continued to advise the executive branch on matters of east Asian foreign policy until 1981.
Oksenberg served as director of the University of Michigan Center for Chinese Studies from 1989 to 1991. He left Michigan in January 1992 to become President of the East-West Center, a federally finances research and training institute in Honolulu, Hawaii. From 1995 until his death in 2001, Oksenberg was associated with the Asia-Pacific Research Center at Stanford University.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Academic and Professional Files; Publication Files; Course Materials; Student Files; University of Michigan Files; Research and Other Projects; Consulting; Topical Files; Photographs; and China - Special Files.
Michel Oksenberg papers document Oksenberg's activities as teacher, researcher, policy advisor, and business consultant, as well as his service on several national Chinese studies committees. The normalization of relations between the United States and the People's Republic of China (PRC) had a profound impact on American sinologists; Oksenberg's papers provide an overview of Chinese studies before, during and after normalization, while also furnishing insight into the actual process of normalization.
Subjects:
China--History--1949-; Oksenberg, Michel, 1938-; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; United States--Foreign relations--China.
- Academic and Professional Files (mainly correspondence)
  The Academic and Professional Files series is the largest portion of the collection and offers the richest source of material from which to document Oksenberg's extensive and varied career. This series, consisting mainly of correspondence, but also including memoranda, reports, and other documentation, has been maintained by broad chronological subseries. Because of Oksenberg's many responsibilities and academic commitments and because these files came into the library in several different accessions, there is much overlapping between the several subseries. The researcher is therefore encouraged to examine the container listing carefully for related (though separated) files of interest to his/her research.
  Some of the subseries are arranged by name of individuals. Included in these are prominent sinologists such as A. Doak Barnett and John K. Fairbanks; policy makers W. Michael Blumenthal and Zbigniew Brzezinski; and presidents Nixon, Carter, and Bush. Other subseries are arranged by name of organization. Here the researcher will find Oksenberg's files from his activities with the Committee on Scholarly Communications with the PRC (CSCPRC); the Joint Committee on Contemporary China (JCCS); the National Committee on US-China Relations (NCUSCR); the Social Science Research Council (SSRC); and several other Chinese studies organizations. This series provides a sense of the changing concerns and priorities of American sinologists during the 1970s and 1980s.
  - 1960-1966
    - Columbia University, 1960-1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Stanford University, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967
    - A-P, 16 folders (Box 1)
    - Political Science Department (Box 1)
    - Q-Z, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - 1967-1977
    (People/ organization file)
    - A (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 2)
    - Adams, Mervyn (editing and publishing company)
      - Papers, 1968-1977 (Box 2)
    - Ahn, Byung-Joon (political science professor)
      - Papers, 1969-1977 (Box 2)
    - American Assembly
      - Introductory essay outline, undated (Box 2)
    - American Council of Learned Societies
      - General correspondence, 1976 (Box 2)
      - Joint Committee on Contemporary China (Box 2)
    - American Journal of Political Science, 1975 (Box 2)
    - American Political Science Association (Box 2)
    - The American Political Science Review (re. article reviews) (Box 2)
    - Encyclopedia Americana (re. articles), 1967-April 1976 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor News (re. article), April 1976. (Box 2)
    - Army Correspondence (see Department of) (Box 2)
    - Asia Society
      - General correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      - China Council
        - 1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - 1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - 1977 (Box 2)
    - Asia Survey (re. article reviews), 1971-1977 (Box 2)
    - Association for Asian Studies, Inc., 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Atlantic Richfield (consultant to) (Box 2)
    - Augustana College, Sioux Falls, S.D., 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Australia
      - General correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - Seminar Australian National University, 1970 (Box 2)
    - B (miscellaneous), 1968-1976 (Box 2)
    - Barclay Conference on priorities for funding and development of Chinese Studies (See also Social Science Research Council; also Conferences, Priorities...), 1973 (Box 2)
    - Barnett, A. Doak (professor, Brookings Institute)
      - 1966-1968 (Box 2)
      - 1969-1974 (Box 2)
    - Baum, Richard (political science professor, UCLA)
      - Papers, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Bennett, Gordon (political science professor, University of Texas)
      - Papers, 1968-1975 (Box 2)
    - Bernstein, Thomas (professor of political science)
      - Individual file, 1968-1976 (Box 2)
      - Bernstein and Stanley Lubman (acting law professor and lecturer, UCLA; later trade advisor)
        - Correspondence, 1964-1975 (Box 2)
    - Blumenthal, Michael (chairman and president of the Bendix Corp.)
      - Papers, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - Brazil trip, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Brookings Institute (see also Barnett, A. Doak), 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Brzezinski, Zbigniew (professor at Columbia University and National Security Advisor for Pres. Carter), 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist, magazine of science and public affairs correspondence with Ruth Adams concerning articles, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Bureau of Applied Social Research at Columbia University, 1968 (Box 3)
    - C (miscellaneous)
      - 1968-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1974 (Box 3)
    - Carnegie Corporation, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Carter (James), 1976 (Box 3)
    - Carter China Statements (Oksenberg responses to), 1976 (Box 3)
    - Center for Chinese Research Materials, Washington, D.C., 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - Central Intelligence Agency, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
    - Chang, Parris (political science professor at the University of Michigan and Pennsylvania State University), 1969-1975 (Box 3)
    - Chen, Jack (Chinese emissary and guest university lecturer on China-American relations)
      - General file, 1971-1976 (Box 3)
      - Chen trip to the U.S., 1973 (Box 3)
    - China (see also People's Republic of China)
      - China Clearinghouse (periodical), 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - China's Development Experience (re. correction and changes on contributing articles and editor's replies), 1972-1974 (Box 3)
      - China Institute in America, New York City, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Second National Committee trip to China, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Chamberlain, Heath B. (political science professor at Stanford and the University of British Columbia in Vancouver)
      - Papers, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    - Chinese Flying Seminar (See Great Neck, N.Y.) (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati Council on World Affairs, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
    - College of Lifelong Learning, Wayne State University (re. Oksenberg speech, 1976) (Box 3)
    - Columbia University, New York City (see also: Millbrook Retreat)
      - General correspondence, 1967-1976 (Box 3)
      - China trip, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Dictation, undated (Box 3)
      - Registrar information, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
      - School of Internal Affairs, undated (Box 3)
    - Committee for a Free China, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Committee for New China Policy, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Committee of Concerned Asian Scholars
      - Newsletter, January 1973 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Scholarly Communications
      - General file, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
      - Workshop on Chinese Agriculture, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Comparative Communism (see Conferences, and Studies in) (Box 3)
    - Biomedicine and Public Health developments in mainland China, Columbia University, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Comparative Communism Study, American Council of Learned Societies, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Micro-societal Affairs of the Chinese
      - Political System, American Council of Learned Societies, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Priorities for Funding and Development of Chinese Studies, Social Science Research Council (SSRC) and American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), November, 1973. (See also Barclay Conference; also Social Science Research Council) (Box 3)
    - Contemporary China Studies Committee, Columbia University, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - Council for International Exchange of Scholars, Washington, D.C., 1976 (Box 4)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, New York City
      - General Correspondence, 1969-1976 (Box 4)
      - Chinese Foreign Policy Study Group, Robinson Council, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Vita: on associates and others, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - D (miscellaneous), 1969-1977 (Box 4)
    - Dallin, Alexander (chairman; Executive Committee of Comparative Study of Communist Elites, Columbia University), 1969-1975 (Box 4)
    - Denver trip, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Department of the Army, 1961-1976; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Detroit Council on Foreign Relations, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Dinnerstein, Herbert and Jocie (Johns Hopkins University, Washington, D.C.), 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Ditchley Conference, Stanford University, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Dittmer, Lowell (Assistant professor, Universities Service Centre, Hong Kong), 1977 (Box 4)
    - Doolin, Dennis (Department of the Defense)
      - Papers, 1968-1974 (Box 4)
    - E (miscellaneous), 1971-1977 (Box 4)
    - Eckstein, Alexander (professor of economics and director of the Center for Chinese Studies, University of Michigan)
      - Papers, 1968-1977 (Box 4)
    - Emerson, John Philip (Department of Commerce)
      - Papers, 1968-1976 (Box 4)
    - F (miscellaneous), 1967-1977 (Box 4)
    - Falkenheim, Victor (professor of government at Franklin and Marshall College, Lancaster, Pennsylvania; later professor of Social Sciences, Scarborough College, Toronto), 1969-1977 (Box 4)
    - Fellowships, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Feuerwerker, Albert (director, Center for Chinese Studies, University of Michigan), 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    - Ford Foundation 1971-1975 (includes the Oksenberg paper, "The Development of Chinese Studies in the 1970s Options and Recommendations," ca. 1972), 1970-1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Foreign Service Institute, Department of State, Washington, D.C., 1969-1975 (Box 4)
    - Foreign Policy Association, New York City, 1970-1977 (Box 4)
    - Fulbright, J.W. (U.S. Senator and chairman, Committee on Foreign Relations)
      - Correspondence with and concerning Fulbright Fellowships, 1971 (Box 4)
    - G (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 5)
    - George Washington Conference on Sino-American Relations, December 1976 (Box 5)
    - German Conference on International China Affairs, Hamburg, June-July 1973 (Box 5)
    - Gilmour, Stanley (political science professor, Pennsylvania State University), 1969 (Box 5)
    - Goldstein, Steve (political science professor, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.), 1969-1977 (Box 5)
    - Great Neck, New York, China Flying Seminar (presented by the adult program of the Great Neck Public Schools; Oksenberg was one of five speakers discussing Chinese life and culture), March 1973 (Box 5)
    - Greenblatt, Sidney (political science professor, Drew and Rutgers Universities, New Jersey), 1968-1975 (Box 5)
    - H (miscellaneous), 1967-1977 (Box 5)
    - Harding, Harry (political science professor at Swarthmore (Pa.) and Stanford (Ca.) Universities), 1968-1977 (Box 5)
    - Harvard/Columbia Seminar on World Politics
      - 1st annual meetings, April 1971 (Box 5)
      - 3rd annual meetings, April 1973 (Box 5)
    - Harvard University Press, 1970-1974 (Box 5)
    - Hoover Institute, Stanford University
      - Bibliography of cataloged Chinese publications, October 1969 (Box 5)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1973 (Box 5)
    - I (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 5)
    - I.B.M., 1969 (Box 5)
    - Imperialism Seminar, Stanford University, May 1967 (Box 5)
    - Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan, Publications on services, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - International Arts and Sciences Press (New York publishers), 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - International Studies Association (includes Comparative Interdisciplinary Study Session (CISS), Minneapolis, Minnesota), 1971-1973 (Box 5)
    - J (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 5)
    - Jackson, Henry (U.S. Senator), 1974 (Box 5)
    - Jacobs, J. Bruce (Columbia graduate and lecturer in politics at La Trobe University, Victoria, Australia), 1972-1977 (Box 5)
    - Japan correspondence, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Jobs (recommendations by Oksenberg and replies from institutions), 1971-1974 (Box 5)
    - Journal of Asian Studies (University of Chicago periodical), 1971-1977 (Box 5)
    - Joint Committee on Contemporary China, Social Science Research Council, New York City
      - General correspondence, 1971-1977; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Advanced Training in Chinese Studies, applicants, 1975 (Box 5)
      - Minutes of meeting, October 22-23, 1976 (Box 5)
      - Programs and minutes, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - K (miscellaneous), 1966-1977 (Box 6)
    - Kau, Ying-Mao (political science professor, Brown University, Rhode Island), 1975-1977 (Box 6)
    - Kincaid, William H. (Major, U.S. Air Force, and Communist Studies Manager, Air Command and Staff College) (see also Maxwell Air Force Base), 1975-1976 (Box 6)
    - Klein, Donald (professor at East Asian Institute of Columbia University, New York City, and later political science professor at Tufts University, Medford, Mass), 1968-1976 (Box 6)
    - Kovenoch, Paul (member of U.N. Development Program in Taipei, Taiwan), 1970-1972 (Box 6)
    - Kraus, Richard (student of the Inter-university Language Program in Taipei, Taiwan and sociology professor at the University of Illinois at Urbana, Champaign), 1971-1977 (Box 6)
    - L (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 6)
    - Lai Fung-wai, Frances (doctoral student at the University of Hawaii and at the Universities Service Centre, Hong Kong), 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    - Lampton, David Michael (student at Stanford University and the Universities Service Centre; later assistant professor of political science at Ohio State University), 1973-1977 (Box 6)
    - Lau, Larry (professor of economics at Stanford University) Papers concerning joint project on contemporary China, 1968-1971 (Box 6)
    - Lardy, Nicolas (assistant professor of economics at Yale University), 1974-1976 (Box 6)
    - Lee Hong Yung (political science professor, Earlham College), 1975-1977 (Box 6)
    - Levine, Steven I. (research associate, East Asian Institute, Columbia University), 1975-1977 (Box 6)
    - Lewis, John (political science professor, Stanford University), 1968-1975 (Box 6)
    - Li, Victor (law school professor at Stanford and the University of Hawaii), 1970-1977 (Box 6)
    - Li Ao (Chinese editor and authority on modern Chinese history) information concerning his arrest by authorities, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Lieberthal, Kenneth (assistant political science professor at Swarthmore College), 1969-1977 (Box 6)
    - Little, Brown & Company, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Loh, Philip, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Lubman, Stanley (active law school professor at UCLA and Washington, D.C. attorney) (See also Bernstein, Thomas), 1968-1977 (Box 6)
    - Luce (Henry) Foundation Proposals, 1975-1977; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - M (miscellaneous), 1967-1977 (Box 7)
    - MacFarquhar, Roderick (Royal Institute of International Affairs, London), 1971-1977 (Box 7)
    - MacInnis, Donald E. (China program director, East Asian Department, Division of Overseas Ministries, National Council of the Churches of Christ), 1969-1973 (Box 7)
    - Maru, Rushikesh (PhD. candidate in political science at the University of Michigan), 1975-1976 (Box 7)
    - Mass Communications, Inc., Westport, Conn. (producer and distributor of educational films), 1975 (Box 7)
    - Mathematica, Bethesda, Maryland
      - Letter requesting book on Chinese agriculture, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Maxwell Air Force Base (see also Kincaid, William)
      - General correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 7)
      - Published material on the Air War College, 1974-1977; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Mexico, Conference on Government in China, Cuernavace, Mexico, February 1969 (Box 7)
    - Michigan, University of Michigan
      - General file, 1972-1976 (Box 7)
      - Business School, seminar on China, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
      - Political Science Department
        - General correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
        - Center for Chinese Studies
          - General file, 1974-1977 (Box 7)
          - Executive meetings, 1976-1977 (Box 7)
          - Governance Committee, 1975 (Box 7)
        - Colloquias on comparative politics, 1976 (Box 7)
        - Economies seminar notes, undated (Box 7)
        - Tenure decisions for the department, undated (Box 7)
      - Press (readers report on Susan Ogden article on Chinese foreign policy), undated (Box 7)
    - Mid-America Committee for International Business and Government Cooperation, Chicago, meetings, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Milbrook Retreat faculty discussions about East Asian Institute's Program at Columbia University, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Muller, David (Masters student at the University of Michigan and Naval officer), 1974-1976 (Box 7)
    - Murphy, Rhoads (associate director, Center for Chinese Studies, University of Michigan), 1973-1975 (Box 7)
    - N (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 7)
    - Nathan, Andrew J. (assistant professor, East Asian Institute, Columbia University), 1971-1977 (Box 7)
    - National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (see also Roundtable on China)
      - General file, 1975; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - General file, 1976 (Box 8)
      - Membership and Executive committees, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
      - National Committee, includes re-evaluation report, 1973-1975; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Travel information, 1975 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous minutes of Board of Directors and Executive committees, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - National Council for U.S.-China Trade
      - General file, 1973-1977 (Box 8)
      - Conference on China's Agriculture, November 1976 (Box 8)
      - Information package, 1975 (Box 8)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1975-1976
      - Papers on China (Box 8)
    - National Science Foundation, Washington, D.C., 1971-1976 (Box 8)
    - National Security Council
      - Report on China Delegation visit, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Letter describing Oksenberg functions on the National Security Council, 1977 (Box 8)
      - Newsweek, 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - O (miscellaneous), 1967-1976 (Box 8)
    - Overseas Development Council, Washington, DC, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
    - P (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 8)
    - Parrish, William (sociology professor, University of Chicago), 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - Peking Arts and Crafts Corporation, White Plains, New York, 1970 (Box 8)
    - People's Republic of China
      - Correspondence with various government officials, 1971-1973 (Box 8)
    - Personal Correspondence
      - General file, 1971-1976 (Box 8)
      - University and other professional material, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Pittsburgh, University of, Center for International Studies, 1969-1971 (Box 9)
    - Pollack, Jonathan (Harvard student of international studies), 1974-1976 (Box 9)
    - Praeger Publishers, New York, New York
      - General file, 1969-1977 (Box 9)
      - Correspondence concerning Oksenberg book on the Chinese Communist Bureaucracy, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Prentice Hall Publishers, concerning Oksenberg articles, 1970-1977 (Box 9)
    - Problems of Communism (periodical published by the U.S. Information Agency), 1970-1976 (Box 9)
    - Public Relations, Oksenberg trip to China in, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Q (miscellaneous), 1973 (Box 9)
    - R (miscellaneous), 1968-1977 (Box 9)